Luis Guillermo Natera Orozco

Data Analyst

natera@hey.com luisnatera.com +36-30-846-91-65 GitHub.com/NateraLuis Linkedin.com/in/Natera

Motivated, interdisciplinarity team-work oriented, and responsible Data Analyst with significant experience working in urban mobility and data analysis. Highly educated, finishing a Ph.D. in Network Science from the Central European University, where I developed new data methods for the analysis of large-scale urban mobility network data, along with the designing of new algorithms to quantify urban liveability and connectivity improvement for bicycle infrastructure networks.

I am interested in the intersection between data analysis and urban mobility as a way to improve our cities towards a more sustainable future.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Network Science, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary. 2021 (expected)

M.A. Communication of Science and Culture, ITESO, Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2015

Academic Visit. Center for Civic Media, MIT Media Lab, Boston, USA. 2015

B.Arch. Architecture, ITESO, Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2010

Academic Visit. Universidad de Valparaíso, Valparíso, Chile. 2012

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data Management

PostgreSQL, PostGIS, Data Analysis, Pattern & Trend Identification, Data Visualization

Computational tools

Python (+5 years experience), Jupyter Notebooks & Jupyter Lab stack, Django (intermediate), HTML (intermediate), CSS (intermediate), Javascript (beginner), SQL (intermediate), ETpX(intermediate), Git + GitHub, GitLab, Bitbucket, Ci/Cd

Research methods

Network & data science research methodologies, Data mining, Statistical analysis

WORK EXPERIENCE

Agglomeration and Social Networks research Lab

Research fellow

07/2021 - Present

Urban mobility and COVID-19

Analyzed mobility data (GPS traces) to model and provide insights regarding the impact of COVID-19 in the urban mobility of Budapest. The analysis has the objective to understand where are the most susceptibles areas in a city to be economically afected by the lack human movement.

Technology stack: Python (OSMnx, igraph, GeoPandas, movingPandas, and more.), PostgreSQL, PostGIS, Linux Server, Google Maps API, and more.

Cities Observatory (ITESM)

Data and network science consultant 05/2020 - Present

Accesibility and mobility analysis

Help and coordinate with the data science team the developing of a methodology to measure urban accessibility in 75 mexican cities using open data, such as OpenStreetMap, national directory of economic units, and other sources.

Technology stack: Python (OSMnx, igraph, GeoPandas, Matplotlib, and more.), PostgreSQL, PostGIS, AWS (RDS, S3, EC2) and more.

Air quality during COVID-19 pandemic lockdown

Design and develop a method to measure the changes in air quality for the cities of Mexico City, Guadalajara, and Monterrey during the lockdown of the COVID-19 pandemic, and the impact of reduce urban mobility.

Technology stack: Python (OSMnx, GeoPandas, Pandas, and more).

LAC_analytics

Co-founder

01/2020 - Present

City Intelligence

Development of a data-driven web platform and API for the analysis of cities and amenities. Some applications of the platform and the data are: location intelligence for real estate, traffic, and public transport, and the analysis of the urban mobility of the city.

Technology stack: Django, Python for data processing, PostgreSQL, PostGIS, AWS (RDS, S3, EC2), HTML, JavaScript.

Evaluation of air quality and urban environment

Development and coordination for a methodology to estimate the quality of air in the area where a new public transport system is being built. The collected data was used to create a baseline to compare the quality of air in the area befor and after the new transport system starts

opperating. This project was a collaboration within multiple actors, including Google.org, and the Government of Jalisco.

Technology stack: Python (GeoPandas, Pandas, Matplotlib, and more), APIs.

Central European University

Ph.D. Researcher

08/2017 - Present

Multimodal Fingerprint of Urban Transportation Networks

Development of a methodology and computational methods for the analysis of urban form in multiple cities around the world. The detection of patterns in the urban mobility infrastructure is useful to understand the urban mobility of a city, and to predict the future of the city.

Technology stack: Python (data collection, cleaning, and modeling), Linux Servers.

Bicycle infrastructure network analysis

Development of algorithms to evaluate and improve the connectivity of bicycle infrastructure networks. The algorithms where applied to fifteen different cities in the world, and the results were published in the journal Royal Society Open Science.

Technology stack: Scientific Python (data collection, cleaning, and modeling), QGIS, Linux Servers.

Quantifying life quality as walkability

Analysis of pedestrian urban accesibility metrics to quantify the liveability of a given city. The project was developed for the Budapest municiaplity as part of a strategy to dectect oportunities around the city and to develop data-driven public policies.

Technology stack: Scientific Python (data collection, cleaning, and modeling), Linux Servers, Statistical modelling.

Signa Lab

Executive Coordinator

08/2016 - 08/2017

Online social networks analysis

Executive coordinator of a social media analysis laboratory. I coordinated the research and development of methodologies to analyze social media data (Twitter, Facebook, and Youtube) to identify patterns and trends in online conversation.

Technology stack: Python (data collection, cleaning), Gephi, Tableau.

Mesura

Networks Analyst

10/2015 - 08/2017

Online social networks analysis

Analyst of social networks, I worked with multinational clients to analyze and improve their social media presence. I developed tools to automatize the data collection with the use of APIs.

Technology stack: Python (data collection), Gephi, Tableau.

IMTJ (Mobility Institute of the State of Jalisco)

Analyst

1/2015 - 10/2015

Sustainable urban mobility

Analyst of urban mobility, I worked with a team of urban and mobility planners to develop the public policies and technical specifications for the operation of the first bike share system in Gudalajara, Jalisco. México. The project was a collaboration with the Government of Jalisco and the municipalities of Guadalajara and Zapopan.

Technology stack: AutoCAD, QGIS.

Colectivo Triciclo

Co-Founder, Principal Architect

8/2010 - 1/2015

Architecture and urban design

I cofounded my own architecture studio. I was responsible for the design of private houses and the development of urban interventions, such as a pop-up neighborhood reading quiosc.

Technology stack: AutoCAD, QGIS.

OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE

Teaching

07/2017 - Present

Python for Social Scientist

I have taught introductory Python courses for social scientists in multiple places, such as Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences, European Consortium of Political Research, and the Central European University.

Technology stack: Jupyter Notebooks, Google Colab.

Introduction to Network Science

I have taught deveolped and taught introduction courses to Network Science for non-technical people in interdiscipliary settings. Such courses were developed to facilitate the undestangind of complex systems in a friendly and interactive way.

Technology stack: Jupyter Notebooks, Google Colab, offline activities.

AWARDS

2020 Award for Advanced Doctoral Students. Central European University

Best lighting talk award. International Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications.

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS AND SERVICE

Professional Affiliations

Network Science Society

Python Software Foundation

SICC Italian Society for Chaos and Complexity

Service

Scientific Data Reviewer

Ph.D. program representative, Central European University, DNDS, 2019-20

Co-organizer Data Stories visualization exhibition, Central European University, DNDS, 2018-19

LANGUAGES

Spanish Native

English Professional proficiency

Updated August 2021

APPENDIX

ACADEMIC PUBLICATIONS

- Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez, G., Szell, M. "Data-driven strategies for optimal bicycle network growth" *Royal Society Open Science*, 2020. 7: 201130. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.201130
- Natera Orozco, L.G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez, G., Szell, M. "Extracting the multimodal fingerprint of urban transportation networks" *Transport Findings*, 2020. https://doi.org/10.32866/001c.13171
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Deritei, D., Vancso, A., Vasarhelyi, O. "Quantifying life quality as walkability on urban networks" In: Cherifi H., Gaito S., Mendes J., Moro E., Rocha L. (eds) Complex Networks and Their Applications VIII. COMPLEX NETWORKS 2019. Studies in Computational Intelligence, 2019, pp. 905–918.
- Natera Orozco, L. G. "Un cambio de la comunicación gubernamental y política. De los medios de comunicación a las redes sociales." *Informe Anual Q Medios 2018*, edited by Bernal, G. Jalisco, Mexico: ITESO.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Reguillo, R. "Comunicación y cambio social: participación política e internet en Jalisco" *Enciclopedia Jaliscience de la Comunicación.*, edited by Orozco, G., Reguillo, R. Jalisco, Mexico: Universidad de Guadalajara.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., (as Signa_Lab) "Battle of the hashtags: Mapping the online conversation surrounding Mexico's gas price" *Global Voices*.
- Natera Orozco, L. G. "Comunicación, ciudad e internet: flujos de información urbana en entornos digitales" VI Seminatio Internacional de Investigación en Urbanismo. Bogota, Colombia.

Manuscripts in Preparation and Development

- Natera Orozco, L. G., Alessandretti, L., Szell, M., Battiston, F. "Multimodal transportation and mobility in urban networks" Under review at *Transportation*
- Tupikina, L., Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F. "A comparative analysis of station and dockless bike share systems."

CONFERENCE AND INVITED TALKS

- 2021 *Invited talk:* Bauhaus-Universität Weimar, Germany.
- 2021 *Invited talk:* URBANUM. Budapest, Hungary.
- 2021 *Invited talk:* Graph data science. Manning Publications.
- 2020 *Invited talk:* Science, Technology and Innovation Council. Hidalgo, Mexico.
- 2020 *Invited talk:* Neo Urban Networks Workshop. Paris, France.
- 2020 *Invited talk:* PIP Ciudad Futuro. Guadalajara, Mexico.

2019 Conference: VIII Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications. Lisbon, Portugal. 2019 Invited talk: Data Science MeetUp. Timisoara, Romania. 2019 *Invited talk:* FabLab, West University of Timisoara, Timisoara, Romania. 2019 Conference: Cycling Research Board Meeting. Delft, Netherlands. 2019 Invited talk: 4D Cities, Multi-Actor Systems Department, TU Delft. Delft, Netherlands. 2019 *Invited talk:* Mobile and Social Computing Lab, Fondazione Bruno Kessler. Trento, Italy. 2019 *Conference:* The Network Science Society Conference. Burlington, USA. 2019 Invited talk: ANET-Talks, ANET Lab, Hungarian Academy of Science. Budapest, Hungary. 2018 Invited talk: Signa_Lab, ITESO. Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2018 Conference: SICC Workshop ComplexCity@PoliTo. Turin, Italy. 2015 Invited talk: Encuentro de Urbanismo Alternativo, Centro Cultural de España en México. Mexico City, Mexico. 2015 *Invited talk:* II Simposio de ciudades y territorios incluyentes "Derecho a la Ciudad", Universidad Autónoma de Yucatán. Merida, Mexico. 2013 Conference: Future of Places. Stockholm, Sweden.

GRANTS AND FELLOWSHIPS

Write-up grant. Central European University
Registration grant. International Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications
Ph.D. conference travel grant. CEU Budapest Foundation
Registration grant. NetSci
Travel grant. Department of Network and Data Science, Central European University
Doctoral grant. Central European University.
Academic Stay at MIT. Mexican National Council of Science and Technology
Master Studies Grant. Mexican National Council of Science and Technology

DETAILED TEACHING EXPERIENCE

GESIS – Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences

Introduction to Computation Social Sciences with Python. GESIS Fall Seminar in Computational Social Science. Co-taught with Orsyola Vásárhelyi

European Consortium for Political Research

Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Summer Virtual Methods School 2021

2021 Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Winter Virtual Methods School 2021 Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Summer Virtual Methods 2020 School 2020 **Central European University** 2020 Teaching Assistant, Scientific Python 2019 Teaching Assistant, Statistical Methods in Network Science **ITESO** 2019 Network Science (Summer 2019) Invited lecturer, co-taught with Diego Arredondo (ITESO) 2017 Network Science (Summer 2017) Co-taught with Emma Towlson (Northeastern University), Sean P. Cornelius (Northeastern University), and Ricardo Zavala (ITESO) 2015–17 Communication, Culture and Society (Spring 2016, 2017) 2015–16 Social Systems Theory (Fall 2015, 2016)